is that people's courage in this regard gets contagious, and so although I and the other journalists with whom I was working were certainly aware of the risk — the United States continues to be the most powerful country in the world and doesn't appreciate it when you disclose thousands of their secrets on the Internet at will — seeing somebody who is a 29-year-old ordinary person who grew up in a very ordinary environment exercise the degree of principled courage that Edward Snowden risked, knowing that he was going to go to prison for the rest of his life or that his life would unravel, inspired me and inspired other journalists and inspired, I think, people around the world, including future whistleblowers, to realize that they can engage in that kind of behavior as well. BG: I'm curious about your relationship with Ed Snowden, because you have spoken with him a lot, and you certainly continue doing so, but in your book, you never call him Edward, nor Ed, you say "Snowden." How come? GG: You know, I'm sure that's something for a team of psychologists to examine. (Laughter) I don't really know. The reason I think that, one of the important objectives that he actually had, one of his, I think, most important tactics, was that he knew that one of the ways to distract attention from the substance of the revelations would be to try and personalize the focus on him, and for that reason, he stayed out of the media. He tried not to ever have his personal life subject to examination, and so I think calling him Snowden is a way of just identifying him as this important historical actor rather than trying to personalize him in a way that might distract attention from the substance. Moderator: So his revelations, your analysis, the work of other journalists, have really developed the debate, and many governments, for example, have reacted, including in Brazil, with projects and programs to reshape a little bit the design of the Internet, etc. There are a lot of things going on in that sense. But I'm wondering, for you personally, what is the endgame? At what point will you think, well, actually, we've succeeded in moving the dial? GG: Well, I mean, the endgame for me as a journalist is very simple, which is to make sure that every single document that's newsworthy and that ought to be disclosed ends up being disclosed, and that secrets that should never have been kept in the first place end up uncovered. To me, that's the essence of journalism and that's what I'm committed to doing. As somebody who finds mass surveillance odious for all the reasons I just talked about and a lot more, I mean, I look at this as work that will never end until governments around the world are no longer able to subject entire populations to monitoring and surveillance unless they convince some court or some entity that the person they've targeted has actually done something wrong. To me, that's the way that privacy can be rejuvenated. BG: So Snowden is very, as we've seen at TED, is very articulate in presenting and portraying himself as a defender of democratic values and democratic principles. But then, many people really find it difficult to believe that those are his only motivations. They find it difficult to believe that there was no money involved, that he didn't sell some of those secrets, even to China and to Russia, which are clearly not the best friends of the United States right now. And I'm sure many people in the room are wondering the same question. Do you consider it possible there is that part of Snowden we've not seen yet? GG: No, I consider that absurd and idiotic. (Laughter) If you wanted to, and I know you're just playing devil's advocate, but if you wanted to sell secrets to another country, which he could have done and become extremely rich doing so, the last thing you would do is take those secrets and give them to journalists and ask journalists to publish them, because it makes those secrets worthless. People who want to enrich themselves do it secretly by selling secrets to the government, but I think there's one important point worth making, which is, that accusation comes from people in the U.S. government, from people in the media who are loyalists to these various governments, and I think a lot of times when people make accusations like that about other people — "Oh, he can't really be doing this for principled reasons, he must have some corrupt, nefarious reason" — they're saying a lot more about themselves than they are the target of their accusations, because — (Applause) — those people, the ones who make that accusation, they themselves never act for any reason other than corrupt reasons, so they assume that everybody else is plagued by the same disease of soullessness as they are, and so that's the assumption. (Applause) BG: Glenn, thank you very much. GG: Thank you very much. BG: Glenn Greenwald. (Applause)
que dans ces situations, le courage des gens est contagieux. Donc même si mes confrères journalistes et moi-même étions conscients du risque - les États-Unis sont le pays le plus puissant de la planète et n'apprécient pas que l'on révèle leurs secrets par milliers sur Internet à volonté, voir une personne de 29 ans, une personne ordinaire, qui a grandi dans un environnement tout à fait ordinaire, faire preuve d'un courage moral aussi important que celui d'Edward Snowden, sachant qu'il irait en prison jusqu'à sa mort ou que sa vie s'effondrerait, m'a inspiré, a inspiré mes confrères et je pense, des gens du monde entier. Même de futurs informateurs, qui ont compris qu'ils pouvaient aussi s'engager dans de telles pratiques. BG : J'aimerais connaître vos liens avec Ed Snowden, car vous lui avez beaucoup parlé, et vous continuez très certainement, mais dans votre livre, vous ne l'appelez pas Edward, ou Ed, vous utilisez « Snowden ». Pourquoi ? GG : C'est certainement une chose qui pourrait être examinée par une équipe de psychologues. Je ne sais pas vraiment, mais il pourrait avoir une raison : l'un de ses objectifs les plus importants, et l'une de ses tactiques les plus importantes, était qu'il savait qu'une manière de détourner l'attention du contenu des révélations serait d'essayer de diriger l'attention sur lui. De ce fait, il s'est éloigné des médias. Il a tenté d'éviter que sa vie privée ne soit examinée. Je pense que l'appeler Snowden est une façon de le présenter comme un important acteur de l'Histoire plutôt que de lui donner un relief particulier qui aurait pu détourner l'attention de la véritable question. BG : Ses révélations et le travail des journalistes ont beaucoup nourri le débat et plusieurs gouvernements ont réagi, avec des projets et des programmes pour remanier le concept d'Internet. De nombreuses choses vont aujourd'hui dans ce sens. Mais je voudrais savoir : vous, personnellement, quel aboutissement souhaitez-vous ? A quel moment penserez-vous : « Nous avons réussi à faire bouger les choses » ? GG : Le dénouement pour moi, en tant que journaliste, est très simple. Il faut qu'on soit sûr que chaque document digne d'intérêt, digne d'être divulgué, soit divulgué, que des secrets qui ne devraient pas l'être soient dévoilés. Voilà l'essence du journalisme et voilà dans quoi je m'engage. Comme je trouve odieuse la surveillance de masse pour toutes les raisons que j'ai citées, mon travail aboutira quand les gouvernements du monde entier ne pourront plus soumettre les populations au contrôle et à l'espionnage sauf s'ils convainquent un tribunal ou une entité que la personne ciblée a vraiment agi de façon illégale. Voilà selon moi la façon de restaurer le droit à la vie privée. BG : On a vu, à un événement TED, que Snowden se présente comme un défenseur des valeurs démocratiques et des principes démocratiques, Pourtant, beaucoup de gens ont du mal à croire qu'il n'avait pas d'autres motivations. Ils ont du mal à croire qu'il n'y avait pas d'argent en jeu, qu'il n'a pas vendu ses secrets à la Chine ou la Russie, qui ne sont pas de bons amis des États-Unis en ce moment. Je suis sûr que beaucoup de gens se posent la question : est-il possible qu'il y ait une facette de Snowden que nous n'avons pas encore vue ? GG : Non, je trouve ça absurde et idiot. (Rires) Je sais que vous jouez juste l'avocat du diable, mais si vous voulez vendre des secrets à un autre pays, ce que Snowden aurait pu faire, et devenir très riche, la dernière chose à faire serait de les communiquer à la presse, car ils perdraient toute leur valeur. Les gens qui veulent s'enrichir vendent leurs secrets discrètement. Je pense qu'il est crucial de préciser que ces accusations proviennent de représentants du gouvernement américain, de personnes au sein des médias loyales à ces différents gouvernements. Je pense que la plupart des gens qui disent : « Je ne crois pas que Snowden ait agi à cause de ses principes, il doit avoir des raisons perverses et infâmes. » en disent beaucoup plus sur eux-mêmes que sur la cible de leurs accusations, car... (Applaudissements) ces personnes, celles qui émettent ces accusations, agissent toujours en fonction de leurs intérêts corrompus. Ils pensent donc que tout le monde est infesté comme eux, par cette maladie qui est l'absence d'âme, d'où leur hypothèse. (Applaudissements) BG : Merci beaucoup, Glenn. GG : Merci beaucoup. BG : Glenn Greenwald. (Applaudissements)